So in a future day, I'm going to be training, fine tuning a model and creating a fine tuned model.
그래서 앞으로는 모델을 훈련하고 미세 조정하고 미세 조정 모델을 만들 거예요
And what I'm going to do now is load in one of the ones that that I've saved in the future, confusingly,
이제 제가 할 일은 미래에 저장해둔 것 중 하나를 로드하는 겁니다 무슨 말인지
if you see what I mean.
아시겠죠
Uh, and that will allow you to see the architecture of it, to get a sense of it.
Get it로 건축물을 보고 감을 잡을 수 있어요
And you do that by loading in not a base model.
기본 모델이 아닌 걸 로드해 그걸 하죠
Not not one of these, um, uh, auto model for causal LLM from pre-trained, but instead a Peft model,
미리 훈련받은 인과적 LLM용 자동차 모델 말고 페프트 모델요 매개 변수
a parameter efficient fine tuned model from pre-trained.
효율적인 미세 조정 모델이죠
And I tell it the base model, which is the one that we've just got right here.
기본 모델이라고 하죠 여기 있는 거요
And fine tune model.
미세 튜닝 모델이에요
This is the name of the model that I saved after I did this.
제가 이걸 한 후 저장한 모델 이름이에요
Laura fine tuning.
로라 파인 튜닝이에요
And I'm doing this just to show you what it looks like.
어떤 모습인지 보여 드리려고 이렇게 하는 거예요
Uh, and this is one that that will run very quickly because it's relatively small.
이건 아주 빨리 달릴 수 있어요 비교적 작으니까요
Uh, let's have a look at the size.
크기를 한번 보죠
So the memory footprint of this is Gigabytes.
메모리 공간은 기가바이트예요
And that should be familiar to you because it's very close to this.
이것과 아주 비슷하니 익숙하실 거예요
Uh, it is about 100MB difference between them.
100MB 정도 차이가 나요
Let's have a look at it.
한번 보죠
So here is the architecture of this thing.
이게 그 구조예요
Uh, and now, yeah, I no longer play that trick.
이제 그 장난은 안 쳐요
This is definitely different to what we saw before.
전에 봤던 것과는 확실히 달라요
And let me tell you what we're seeing.
지금 상황을 말씀드리죠
So first of all, everything you're seeing up to this point here is the same up to the point where we
우선, 여기 보이는 모든 건 라마가 있는 32개의
have the 32 Lama decoder layers.
층까지 똑같아요
And now we get to the this attention layer and we have the Q proj the k proj the V and the O uh, proj
이제 주의력 레이어가 나왔네요 Q 프래, K 프래, V, O 프래, O가
uh layers.
있죠
And what you'll see is that each of these has a base layer.
여기 보시면 각각의 베이스 레이어가 있어요
And then it has lora A and lora B.
로라 A와 로라 B도 있어요
And these are the A and B matrices that I told you about before, uh which have come in here and you'll
여기가 아까 말한 A와 B 행렬들이에요 여기 32번
see this number 32 here.
보이죠?
That is the R that I mentioned before, the Lora rank.
제가 전에 말했던 로라 등급이에요
They are 32 rank matrices.
32급 행렬들이에요
Um, and uh, yeah.
네, 맞아요
The, the uh, if, if you're in if you're familiar with the way that these the matrix math works out,
이 매트릭스 수학이 어떻게 적용되는지 잘 아신다면 32차원적 개념을 서로
you can see this is designed so that the 32 dimensions will can be multiplied together in such a way
곱할 수 있도록 설계된 것을 보실 수 있습니다 이 기본 레이어에 적용할 수 있도록
as it can be applied to this base layer and be used to make a small shift to that base layer.
말이죠 그리고 이 기본 레이어에서는 약간의 변화를 줄 수 있죠
I'm again being a bit hand-wavy because I want to get bogged down in the theory, but the idea is that
물결무늬를 만들고 있어요 이론에 빠져들게 하려고요 비트들을
these will be multiplied together.
곱할 거예요
Lora A and Lora.
로라 A와 로라요
B together with alpha, the scaling factor, and that will then be used as a delta to apply.
B와 알파를 함께 배율 요인으로 선택하고 델타로 적용하는 거죠
On top of this base layer, there is also another hyperparameter called dropout.
이 기본 층 위에는 드롭아웃이라는 하이퍼파라미터도 있어요
And we'll be talking about that later.
그 얘긴 나중에 하죠
That's not one of the big three that we talked about this week.
이번 주에 얘기했던 세 가지 중 하나가 아니죠
but you'll see that feature a few times here.
이 기능은 여기서 몇 번 보실 거예요
And so if we look at the other, uh, of the of the four target modules, you'll see that they all have
네 개의 목표 모듈 중 다른 모듈을 보면 전부 로라 A와 로라 B가
a Laura A and a Laura B here, where again, we have a Laura A and a Laura B, and finally a Laura A
여기 있는데 다시 말씀드리면 로라 A와 로라 B가 있고 마지막으로 로라
and Laura B here, Laura A and Laura B, and so that is where our adapter matrices have been inserted
A와 로라 B가 여기 로라 A와 로라 B가 있죠 여기서 어댑터 매트릭스가 라마 경계의 구조에
into the Lama architecture to adapt the bigger model, but with much fewer dimensions.
삽입되어 더 큰 모델을 적용하지만 훨씬 적은 범위에서 적용해요
Uh, these, these 32 dimensions as specified by our R hyperparameter.
R 하이퍼파라미터에 명시된 32개의 차원이죠
Uh, nothing else has been changed.
다른 건 바뀐 게 없어요
The the multi-layer perceptron layer is exactly the same.
다층 과셉트론 층도 정확히 같아요
Um, and everything else is the same.
다른 건 다 똑같아요
And so just to mention again, we're trying not to get bogged down in this, but the you could look
다시 한번 말씀드리지만 이 문제에 휘말리지 않으려고 노력해요 하지만 과거를
back to convince yourself that this is the number of dimensions in those, those four, uh, Matrices
돌아보면 납득이 돼요 IQ, IQ, IQ, IQ, IQ 4개 행렬에는 치수의 수가 있다는
there is.
걸요
Each one has a Laura A and a Laura B, and I've just multiplied together the dimensions of that matrix
각각 로라 A와 로라 B가 있고 매트릭스의 차원을 조합해서
to tell you how many dimensions, how many weights in total we have across these adapters.
이 어댑터에 있는 무게의 총합을 알려주는 거예요
And then that means for each layer we sum up these four numbers.
그 말은 각 층에서 이 4개의 숫자를 합친다는 거죠
I multiply that by 32 because there are 32 of these groups of modules.
32를 곱합니다. 모듈 그룹이 32개니까요.
And then each of these parameters is a four byte number.
각 매개 변수는 4바이트 숫자죠
It's 32 bits.
32개요
And so I calculate the size and divide that by a million to get it in megabytes.
크기를 계산하고 100만으로 나누면 메가바이트로 get이 되죠
I'm not sure if you're following all this, but hopefully you get a general idea just to give you a
이해가 되시는지 모르겠지만 대략적인 건
sense of perspective, if you add up all of the weights in our Laura adapters, there's a total of 27
이해하셨길 바라요 로라 어댑터의 중량을 모두 더하면 총 2,700만
million parameters and the total size is about 109MB.
개의 매개 변수가 있고 총 크기는 약 109MB예요
So 27 million parameters of size Hundred and nine megabytes.
109MB의 2,700만 매개 변수죠
That's how large our adapters are.
어댑터가 그만큼 크죠
And of course, compare that to the fact that llama overall has 8 billion parameters and is 32GB in
물론 그걸 전체적인 llama 매개 변수가 80억 개인 것과 비교하세요 크기는 32GB죠
So it gives you a sense we're doing a lot here, a lot of parameters and a lot to be trained, but it's
여기서 할 일이 많다는 걸 알 수 있어요 매개 변수도 많고 훈련할 것도 많지만
tiny compared to the monstrosity that is llama 3.1, even the small variant.
흉물스러운 라마 3에 비하면 아주 작죠 1, 작은 변종도요
So this whilst I realize there's been a fair bit of, uh, of, uh, stuff in here that, uh, you may
이 안에 뭐가 많다는 건 알고 있었어요 무슨 말인지 다시 확인해 보세요
have to go back and check and see what I mean, but hopefully it gives you that intuition, that sense
그래도 직감이 돌아올 거예요 저차원 물질을
that we're able to use these lower dimensional matrices to have an impact on the bigger architecture,
이용하면 더 큰 건축물에 영향을 줄 수 있지만 크기가 작을수록
but with a smaller size, smaller number of weights that has to be adjusted.
비트도 더 적게 조정해야 한다는 거죠
Um, and just to give you just a sort of evidence that this number, this 109MB, is the size of the
증거를 보여드리자면 이 숫자, 이 109MB는 얼굴을 안는
parameters I can actually go into hugging face.
데 필요한 파라미터의 크기예요
I'm now in hugging face and I'm looking at where I saved that particular Laura adapter, that fine tuned
얼굴을 끌어안고 있어요 제가 저장한 로라 어댑터를 보고 있죠 미세 튜닝 모델이요
model, and what we'll find.
뭘 찾게 될까요?
When you look at these, you look for something called safe tensors.
이걸 보면 안전한 텐서를 찾죠
That is the file which stores the parameters themselves.
그게 매개 변수 자체를 저장하는 파일이에요
Um, and if you look at this for llama 3.1, you'll see that it's 32GB large.
라마 3을 보시면 알 수 있죠 1번, 32GB로 크게 보이죠
If I look at it for this, you'll see it's 109MB of parameters, 109MB, which matches this estimate
이걸 보면 매개 변수가 109MB인 게 보이죠 여기 추정값과
here, 109MB.
일치해요
That is the size of the parameters that we are fine tuning using this Q Laura technique.
Q 로라 기법으로 세밀하게 조정하고 있는 매개 변수의 크기예요
So I hope at least at the very least, it's given you a decent intuition for what's going on here and
적어도 직관적으로 어떤 일이 일어나고 있는지 파악하셨길
how we're able to pull this trick of being able to fine tune a model without needing to have gigabytes
바랍니다 최적화하는 기가바이트의 데이터 없이도 모델을 미세 조정하는
of data that we are optimizing over.
트릭을 어떻게 구현할 수 있는지도요
And so with that, back to the slides for a wrap up.
이제 마무리로 슬라이드로 돌아가죠